Guide to the Papers of George L. Mosse (1918-1999), 1780-2001 AR 25137 / MF 671
Center for Jewish History, Publisher.
- Series II: Writings and Research, 1750-2001; 25.3 linear feet
  - Subseries 4: Research Notes, undated, 1793-1999; 6.5 linear feet
    - A) Books
      - a) Confronting History
        - Research Notes - Photocopies, undated, 1933-1939, 1960, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - b) Confronting the Nation
        - Research Notes - World War I, undated, 1978, 1987, 1992-1993 (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - c) Crisis of German Ideology
        - Research Notes, undated, 1933-1939, 1967 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - d) Fallen Soldiers
        - Australia, undated, 1974 (Box 22, Folder 5)
        - Bibliographies, undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
        - Cemetery History, undated, 1793-1985 (Box 22, Folder 7)
        - Cemeteries of World War I, undated (Box 22, Folder 8)
        - Cemeteries of World War I - Clippings, undated, 1977-1978, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 9)
        - Cemeteries of World War I - Photocopies, undated, 1915-1984 (Box 22, Folder 10)
        - Cemeteries of World War I - Photocopies, undated, 1915-1979 (Box 22, Folder 11)
        - Chapter II, undated, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 12)
        - Chapter II - the Greek War, undated, 1935, 1969-1984 (Box 22, Folder 13)
        - Chapter II - Photocopies, undated, 1832, 1963-1984 (Box 22, Folder 14)
        - Chapter II - Photocopies, undated, 1937-1984 (Box 22, Folder 15)
        - Chapter IV, undated, 1917, 1928 (Box 22, Folder 16)
        - Chapter V, undated, 1983-1985 (Box 22, Folder 17)
        - Chapter V - Photocopies, 1915-1986 (Box 22, Folder 18)
        - Chapter V - Photocopies, 1915-1986 (Box 22, Folder 19)
        - Chapter VI, undated, 1993 (Box 22, Folder 20)
        - Chapter VI - Photocopies, undated, 1896, 1922-1988 (Box 22, Folder 21)
        - Chapter VII, undated (Box 22, Folder 22)
        - Chapter VII - Films and Photos, undated, 1922-1936, 1975-1978 (Box 22, Folder 23)
        - Chapter VII - Photocopies, undated, 1915-1917, 1940-1976 (Box 22, Folder 24)
        - Chapter VII - Tourism, undated, 1920-1929, 1975-1977 (Box 22, Folder 25)
        - Chapter VII - Toys, undated, 1916-1979 (Box 22, Folder 26)
        - Chapter VIII, undated, 1979 (Box 22, Folder 27)
        - Chapter VIII - Photocopies, undated, 1914-1985 (Box 22, Folder 28)
        - Chapter IX, undated (Box 22, Folder 29)
        - Chapter IX - Pacifism, undated, 1962-1988 (Box 22, Folder 30)
        - Chapter IX - Photocopies, undated, 1930-1986 (Box 22, Folder 31)
        - Chapter X, undated (Box 22, Folder 32)
        - Chapter X - Clippings, 1980-1989 (Box 22, Folder 33)
        - Chapter X - Photocopies, undated, 1965-1983 (Box 23, Folder 1)
        - Cult of Fallen Soldiers, undated, 1921-1938, 1968 (Box 23, Folder 2)
        - Ehrenhaine, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
        - France, Italy, England, undated, 1963-1985 (Box 23, Folder 4)
        - France, Italy, England - Photocopies, undated, 1889, 1916-1985 (Box 23, Folder 5)
        - Greulmärchen, undated, 1960, 1972 (Box 23, Folder 6)
        - Introduction, undated, 1977, 1985 (Box 23, Folder 7)
        - Introduction - Photocopies, undated, 1905, 1928-1987 (Box 23, Folder 8)
        - Monuments aux Morts, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
        - New Material, undated, 1975 (Box 23, Folder 10)
        - Not Used, undated, 1976-1987 (Box 23, Folder 11)
        - Songs, undated, 1916-1979 (Box 23, Folder 12)
        - Spanish Civil War, undated, 1934-1988 (Box 23, Folder 13)
        - War Christmas, undated, 1914-1969 (Box 23, Folder 14)
        - War Graves Commission, undated, 1917-1978 (Box 23, Folder 15)
        - War Memorials, undated, 1961-1983 (Box 23, Folder 16)
        - War of Liberation, undated, 1982-1987 (Box 23, Folder 17)
        - War of Liberation - Photocopies, undated, 1911-1967 (Box 23, Folder 18)
      - e) The Image of Man
        - Bibliography, undated (Box 23, Folder 19)
        - Chapters I and II, undated, 1931, 1967, 1981 (Box 23, Folder 20)
        - Chapter III, undated, 1912, 1987-1990 (Box 23, Folder 21)
        - Chapter IV, undated, 1993 (Box 23, Folder 22)
        - Chapter V, undated, 1990-1993 (Box 23, Folder 23)
        - Chapter V - Photocopies, undated, 1873-1994 (Box 23, Folder 24)
        - Chapter VI, undated, 1993-1994 (Box 23, Folder 25)
        - Chapter VI - Photocopies, 1917-1921, 1944, 1984-1988 (Box 23, Folder 26)
        - Chapter VI - Photocopies, 1923-1925, 1946-1991 (Box 23, Folder 27)
        - Chapter VII, undated, 1933, 1978-1987 (Box 23, Folder 28)
        - Chapter VIII, undated, 1935-1941, 1976-1999 (Box 24, Folder 1)
        - Chapter IX, undated, 1971, 1985-1993 (Box 24, Folder 2)
        - Chapter IX - Androgyny, undated, 1974, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 3)
        - For German Translation - Not Used, undated, 1937-1939, 1986-1995 (Box 24, Folder 4)
        - Fugitive Footnotes, undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
        - Gemeinschaftsunfähigen, undated, 1988 (Box 24, Folder 6)
        - Gentlemen, undated, 1981 (Box 24, Folder 7)
        - Gymnastics, undated, 1893-1949, 1963-1986 (Box 24, Folder 8)
        - Heroes, undated, 1935, 1981-1985 (Box 24, Folder 9)
        - Honor and Dueling, undated, 1897, 1930, 1969-1994 (Box 24, Folder 10)
        - Introduction, undated, 1901, 1936, 1976-1991 (Box 24, Folder 11)
        - Manliness - Not Used, undated, 1859, 1963, 1980-1994 (Box 24, Folder 12)
        - Masculinity Articles, undated, 1889, 1929-1996 (Box 24, Folder 13)
        - Possible Additions, undated, 1882 (Box 24, Folder 14)
        - Psychology, undated, 1938, 1973, 1990 (Box 24, Folder 15)
        - Sittlichkeitsvereine, undated, 1904, 1983 (Box 24, Folder 16)
        - Socialism, undated, 1919, 1958, 1988 (Box 24, Folder 17)
        - Otto Weiniger, undated, 1904-1907, 1985-1992 (Box 24, Folder 18)
        - The Will, undated, 1900, 1906, 1937 (Box 24, Folder 19)
        - Zeit der Götter, undated (Box 24, Folder 20)
      - f) Nationalism and Sexuality
        - Chapter III, 1907-1978 (Box 24, Folder 21)
      - g) Source Readings - Western Civilization in Modern Times
        - Research Notes, 1947? (Box 24, Folder 22)
      - h) Toward the Final Solution: a History of European Racism
        - Research Notes, 1977?, 1988 (Box 24, Folder 23)
    - B) Research Areas
      - a) First World War and the War Experience
        - After World War I, undated, 1914-1977 (Box 24, Folder 24)
        - Boer War, 1903-1940 (Box 24, Folder 25)
        - Celebrations and Parades, undated, 1865, 1901, 1932 (Box 24, Folder 26)
        - The Cult of Death, undated, 1983, 1994 (Box 24, Folder 27)
        - England Before World War I, undated, 1957-1978 (Box 24, Folder 28)
        - France, undated, 1920, 1968, 1973 (Box 24, Folder 29)
        - France's Monument des Morts, undated, 1914-1925, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 1)
        - Friendship - Montherlaut, Henri de, undated, 1941 (Box 25, Folder 2)
        - Friendship and Bildung, undated, 1972-1983 (Box 25, Folder 3)
        - German Art, undated, 1933, 1959, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 4)
        - Health and Doctors, undated, 1908, 1920 (Box 25, Folder 5)
        - The Knights of the Sky, undated, 1918-1993 (Box 25, Folder 6)
        - Memorials and Monuments, undated, 1877, 1928-1994 (Box 25, Folder 7)
        - National Anthems: the Nation Militant, undated, 1920-1981 (Box 25, Folder 8)
        - Nature and War, undated, 1916, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 9)
        - Nazis, undated, 1938-1987 (Box 25, Folder 10)
        - "New Man," Death and War, undated, 1894-1988 (Box 25, Folder 11)
        - Pictorial Material, undated, 1993 (Box 25, Folder 12)
        - Poetry and Literature, undated, 1920-1990 (Box 25, Folder 13)
        - Poetry and Literature, undated, 1931-1988 (Box 25, Folder 14)
        - Second World War, undated (Box 25, Folder 15)
        - Shell-Shock, undated, 1919-1998 (Box 25, Folder 16)
        - Toys and Tourism, undated, 1916, 1920, 1988, 1991 (Box 25, Folder 17)
        - Verdun, undated, 1984 (Box 25, Folder 18)
        - Volksbund für Kreigsgräberfürsorge, undated, 1930-1988 (Box 25, Folder 19)
        - Volunteers, undated, 1916, 1937-1983 (Box 25, Folder 20)
        - War Christmas, undated, 1914-1969 (Box 25, Folder 21)
        - War Experience, undated, 1941-1989 (Box 25, Folder 22)
        - War Experience - Barbusse, Henri, undated, 1918-1928 (Box 25, Folder 23)
        - War Experience - German Communism, 1919-1968 (Box 25, Folder 24)
        - World War I - Bibliographies, undated (Box 25, Folder 25)
        - World War I - Desertion, undated, 1936, 1968-1990 (Box 25, Folder 26)
      - b) Jewish History
        - Auerbach, Berthold, undated, 1867-1978 (Box 26, Folder 1)
        - Benjamin, Walter, undated, 1912, 1985 (Box 26, Folder 2)
        - Deutsch-Jüdische Bildungsbürgertum, undated, 1861-1980 (Box 26, Folder 3)
        - German-Jewish Culture, undated, 1844, 1905 (Box 26, Folder 4)
        - German-Jewish Culture, undated, 1882, 1966-1992 (Box 26, Folder 5)
        - Holocaust and War Materials, undated, 1991, 1996 (Box 26, Folder 6)
        - Jewish Culture, undated, 1851-1985 (Box 26, Folder 7)
        - Jewish Intellectuals, undated, 1927-1976 (Box 26, Folder 8)
        - Jewish Nationalism, undated (Box 26, Folder 9)
        - Jewish Nationalism - Photocopies, undated, 1929-1931, 1964 (Box 26, Folder 10)
        - Jewish Nationalism - Photocopies, undated, 1923-1997 (Box 26, Folder 11)
        - The Jewish Question, undated, 1971-1977 (Box 26, Folder 12)
        - The Jewish Question - Photocopies, undated, 1943-1976 (Box 26, Folder 13)
        - Jewish Soldiers, undated (Box 26, Folder 14)
        - Nordau, Max, undated, 1915-1989 (Box 26, Folder 15)
        - Notebook - Martin Buber and Max Nordau, undated (Box 26, Folder 16)
        - Sholem, Gershom, undated, 1964-1986 (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - c) Political Movements
        - Antisemitism, undated, 1884-1969 (Box 26, Folder 18)
        - Antisemitism, undated, 1922, 1960, 1991-1994 (Box 26, Folder 19)
        - Antisemitism - Protocols of the Learned Elders of Zion, undated (Box 26, Folder 20)
        - Communist Movement in Germany, 1929-1976 (Box 26, Folder 21)
        - European Right - Photocopies, 1934, 1970 (Box 27, Folder 1)
        - Fascism, undated, 1966, 1971-1974, 1997 (Box 27, Folder 2)
        - Fascism - Photocopies, 1957-1994 (Box 27, Folder 3)
        - Fascism and Sexuality, undated, 1978, 1984 (Box 27, Folder 4)
        - Fascism and Sexuality - Photocopies, undated, 1933-1978 (Box 27, Folder 5)
        - Fascism, Nationalism, and Racism - Bibliographies, undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
        - The Fascist Revolution - Introduction, 1996-1998 (Box 27, Folder 7)
        - French Right, undated, 1950 (Box 27, Folder 8)
        - French Right - Boulangerism, undated, 1889-1970 (Box 27, Folder 9)
        - French Right - Camelot du Roi, undated, 1926 (Box 27, Folder 10)
        - French Right - English and German Notes, undated, 1922, 1953 (Box 27, Folder 11)
        - French Socialism, undated (Box 27, Folder 12)
        - Futurism, undated, 1961, 1968 (Box 27, Folder 13)
        - Goebbels, Joseph, undated, 1895, 1952-1971 (Box 27, Folder 14)
        - Hitler, Adolf, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 15)
        - Mass Movements, 1961 (Box 27, Folder 16)
        - National Socialism, undated, 1933-1997 (Box 27, Folder 17)
        - National Socialism and Sexuality, undated, 1944 (Box 27, Folder 18)
        - National Socialism and Sexuality - Männerbund, undated (Box 27, Folder 19)
        - National Socialism - Social Life, undated, 1934, 1954, 1997, 2000 (Box 27, Folder 20)
        - National Socialism - Transparencies, undated (Box 27, Folder 21)
        - National Socialism - World Union of National Socialism (WUNS) Bulletin, 1968-1970 (Box 27, Folder 22)
        - Nationalism, undated, 1913, 1929 (Box 27, Folder 23)
        - Racism, undated, 1863-1923, 1971 (Box 27, Folder 24)
        - Racism, undated, 1863-1987 (Box 27, Folder 25)
        - Racism, undated, 1864-1975 (Box 27, Folder 26)
        - Racism and Sexuality, undated, 1971, 1985, 1990 (Box 27, Folder 27)
        - Racism and Sexuality - Photocopies, undated, 1863, 1928-1992 (Box 27, Folder 28)
        - Racism and Sexuality - Photocopies, undated, 1917-1983 (Box 27, Folder 29)
      - d) Sexuality
        - Bertrand-Rival, J.F., undated, 1799-1801 (Box 28, Folder 1)
        - Brook, Rupert, undated, 1918, 1980 (Box 28, Folder 2)
        - Degeneration, undated, 1895, 1908, 1941-1991 (Box 28, Folder 3)
        - Family, undated, 1795-1989 (Box 28, Folder 4)
        - Friendship, undated, 1750, 1931-1966 (Box 28, Folder 5)
        - Homosexuality, undated, 1998 (Box 28, Folder 6)
        - Homosexuality and French Fascism, 1920-1990 (Box 28, Folder 7)
        - Homosexuality - Photocopies and Reprints, undated, 1796, 1956-1992 (Box 28, Folder 8)
        - Homosexuality - Photocopies of Articles, 1860-1953 (Box 28, Folder 9)
        - Homosexuality - Photocopies of Articles, 1964, 1978-1995 (Box 28, Folder 10)
        - Hysteria, 1950-1991 (Box 28, Folder 11)
        - Lesbians, undated, 1969-1990 (Box 28, Folder 12)
        - Lesbians - Photocopies, undated, 1930-1989 (Box 28, Folder 13)
        - Nudity, undated, 1989 (Box 28, Folder 14)
        - Sexuality, undated, 1791-1985 (Box 28, Folder 15)
        - Sexuality, undated, 1979-1996 (Box 28, Folder 16)
        - Sexuality - Bibliographies, undated (Box 28, Folder 17)
        - Sexuality - Bibliographies, undated (Box 28, Folder 18)
        - Sexuality - Photocopies, undated, 1900-1983 (Box 28, Folder 19)
        - Sexuality - Photocopies, undated, 1847-1931 (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Sexuality - Photocopies, 1973-1986 (Box 29, Folder 2)
        - Sexuality - Photocopies, undated, 1913-1987 (Box 29, Folder 3)
        - Women, undated, 1812, 1980-1986 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - e) Other
        - Art, undated, 1958-1977 (Box 29, Folder 5)
        - Art - Medieval, undated, 1955, 1961 (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - Art - Medieval - Postcards, undated, 1934, 1954-1955 (Box 29, Folder 7)
        - Art - Reproductions, undated, 1935, 1939 (Box 29, Folder 8)
        - Art - Reproductions - Postcards, undated, 1953-1954, 1961, 1979 (Box 29, Folder 9)
        - Art - Reproductions from Calendars, 1945, 1960 (Box 29, Folder 10)
        - Art - Reproductions from Calendars, 1976-1977 (Box 29, Folder 11)
        - Berlin, 1980-1984 (Box 29, Folder 12)
        - Bibliographical Entries, undated (Box 29, Folder 13)
        - Eugen und Marie Schiffer, 1990 (Box 29, Folder 14)
        - German History, undated (Box 29, Folder 15)
        - Interment in Les Milles, undated (Box 29, Folder 15)
        - May, Karl, 1962, 1974 (Box 29, Folder 17)
        - Media, undated (Box 29, Folder 18)
        - Naumann, Friedrich, undated (Box 29, Folder 19)
        - Paleography, 1805 (Box 29, Folder 20)
        - Religious Music, undated (Box 29, Folder 21)
        - Salem School, undated, 1933-1986, 1995? (Box 29, Folder 22)
        - "Sermons sur les Profondeurs Divines", undated (Box 29, Folder 23)
        - Sixteenth Century, undated (Box 29, Folder 24)
  - Subseries 5: Index Cards, undated, 1958-1985; 2.8 linear feet (10 0.4 linear foot index card boxes and 4 0.5 linear foot index card boxes, stacked on top of one another)
    Index cards are cards with handwritten or typed notes on numerous topics. Since Mosse produced many articles and several books on related topics, separating some cards into topics was not possible. Some index cards were located in labeled boxes and these have been separated into their own card file boxes. Some papers were found with the cards containing research notes and bibliographic information; these notes have been kept in this series to preserve original order. Many of the index cards appear to have notes from Mosse's early career since they largely focus on topics such as the English Reformation.
    - Advisory, undated (Box 64)
    - Cambridge - Modern History, undated (Box 65)
    - Holy Pretence, undated (Box 66)
    - Holy Pretence, undated (Box 67)
    - Puritans, undated (Box 68)
    - Puritans, undated (Box 69)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 70)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 71)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 72)
    - Notes with Index Cards - Bibligraphies, undated (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Notes with Index Cards - Book Order Slips from Universitätsbibliothek Giessen, 1979 (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Notes with Index Cards - Fascism, 1985 (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - Notes with Index Cards - French History, 1975 (Box 29, Folder 28)
    - Notes with Index Cards - German-Jewish History, undated (Box 29, Folder 29)
    - Notes with Index Cards - Machiavelli, undated (Box 29, Folder 30)
    - Notes with Index Cards - National Socialism, 1958 (Box 29, Folder 31)
    - Notes with Index Cards - Socialism, undated (Box 29, Folder 32)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1919-2001; 22 linear feet
  The correspondence of George L. Mosse is an essential part of this collection. It provides the researcher with views of George L. Mosse on politics and contemporary trends in the community of historians, and includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence. George L. Mosse's letters document very well both his academic and non-academic activities and plans. The series is divided into six subseries according to the group of recipients and senders.
  The first subseries holds letters of immediate family members. Some of the early letters were written during George L. Mosse's studies at the boarding school Schule Schloss Salem to his parents Hans and Felicia Lachmann Mosse. The researcher can also find letters exchanged among the siblings Rudolf, Hilde and George L. Mosse. However, the majority of their letters is to be found in the following subseries,Legal Correspondence, which primarily consists of correspondence related to restitution of the family property in Germany. Their restitution efforts were carried out in two waves, one in the 1950s and the other one after the fall of the Berlin wall in 1989, when George L. Mosse could finally claim the family property in the territory of the former German Democratic Republic.
  The three subseries that deal with George L. Mosse's professional activities as educator, writer, editor, and mentor can have a great value for better understanding George L. Mosse's work.Subseries 3: Personal contains letters to and from George L. Mosse to and from his friends, collaborators and colleagues. The nature of some of these letters is often mixed, with some being work-related and some rather personal, since so many of his friends were his colleagues as well.
  Subseries 4 is comprised of correspondence that George L. Mosse had with various organizations in two major areas – with publishing firms and their editors and educational institutions. This subseries is related to Series II: Writings and Research, where the texts of his lectures, articles, and other works are located.
  In addition to being a committed educator and lecturer, George L. Mosse was an editor of the Journal of Contemporary History, together with Walter Laquer. The subseries Journal of Contemporary History is made of editorial correspondence with authors and publishers of the journal as well as drafts of articles and their finalized versions. The letters with authors are often complementary to their personal correspondence with George L. Mosse that can be found in Subseries 3: Personal.
  The last subseries,Students, is comprised of correspondence between George L. Mosse and his former students, usually undergraduates. An overwhelming part of this subseries is recommendations and referrals and only a small part of these folders contains actual letters.
  Access restrictions
  Access to series III: Correspondence, 1919-2001: subseries 1-3 (box/folders 30/1-40/41) and subseries 6 (box/folders 51/1-51/259) is restricted to those who receive written permission from the trustees of the George L. Mosse Estate.
  Please contact:
  Leo Baeck Institute
  Center for Jewish History
  15 West 16th Street
  New York, NY 10011
  lbaeck@lbi.cjh.org
  - Subseries 1: Family, undated, 1930-1998; 0.25 linear foot
    Alphabetical
    This subseries contains letters both of the immediate members of the family of George L. Mosse and some other relatives. Next to the earliest letters that George L. Mosse wrote to his parents from various locations, including the boarding school Salem, there are also several letters written by his sister Hilde and brother Rudolf. One can also find several letters by his step-brother Karl Strauch. Some correspondence is written by Felicia Lachmann Mosse to Hans Lachmann. The parents of George L. Mosse were divorced and Hans Lachmann married Karola Lachmann. The Other Family Members file was put together by George L. Mosse and is part of this subseries, unlike correspondence with Eva Noack-Mosse and Eugene Mosse that is part of Subseries 3: Personal.
    Access to subseries 1 is restricted to those who receive written permission from the trustees of the George L. Mosse Estate.
    - Lachmann, Karola, 1933?-1943, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Lachmann-Mosse, Hans, 1930-1943 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Lachmann-Mosse, Hans and Felicia, 1929-1935 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Lachmann-Mosse, Rudolf, 1931-1934 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Mosse, Felicia, undated, 1932, 1940, 1958 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Mosse, Felicia to Hans Lachmann-Mosse, undated, 1943 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Mosse, Hilde, 1931-1977 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Strauch, Karl, 1979-1983, 1996, 1998 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Other Family Members, 1938-1986 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 2: Legal, 1919-1998; 1.25 linear feet
    When the members of the Lachmann-Mosse family left Germany immediately after 1933 they were forced to leave their property behind and lost effective control over many of the family enterprises and real estate. After the war all heirs of Hans Mosse claimed restitution of the property once belonging to the Rudolf Mosse Firm and the family properties. They were successful in reclaiming some of it, but since most of their assets were in the territory of the German Democratic Republic they could not be returned until the 1990s.
    After the fall of the Berlin wall, there was a chance to claim the property once belonging to the Mossse family located in the territory of the former German Democratic Republic. The properties in question were the estate of Schenkendorf(once a military headquarters) and the estates of Gallun and Dyrotz. The Berlin properties consisted of the Mosse publishing house and land property on Oranienburger Street (the building was destroyed) and the palace of Rudolf and Emilie Mosse on Leipziger Square which was completely destroyed, as well as some smaller land properties.
    The heirs worked together with a lawyer based in the United States who collaborated and coordinated the legal strategy with several attorneys in Germany. Among them the most prominent was Carl Hermann. For the later period of restitution in the territory of the former German Democratic Republic,Gesine Fischer-Faul was the leading lawyer. Some of the folders are are thematic and therefore contain material from several lawyers. The legal agenda was often mixed, and copies from one lawyer were sent to other colleages in several copies and basically the original arrangement was preserved.
    Access to subseries 2 is restricted to those who receive written permission from the trustees of the George L. Mosse Estate.
    - A) General Files
      - Account Statements, 1953-1960, 1976 (Box 30, Folder 10)
      - Dyrotz, 1996 (Box 30, Folder 11)
      - Estate of Felicia and Hans Lachmann-Mosse, 1979-1986 (Box 30, Folder 12)
      - Mosse Center, 1995-1996 (Box 30, Folder 13)
      - Mosse Center - Exhibit "Mosse Haus and Tageblatt", 1994 (Box OSL41, Folder 9)